<section>
<name filename="commands">BeanShell Commands</name>

BeanShell commands take the form of pre-defined methods such as print().
BeanShell Commands are are mostly composed of BeanShell scripts, supplied 
in the JAR file.  We'll talk about adding your own commands to the classpath
a bit later.  
<p/>

<h2>Commands Overview</h2>

This is a high level overview of the BeanShell command set.
You can find documentation for all BeanShell commands in the "BeanShell
Commands Documentation" section of this manual.  See also the "BshDoc" 
section which covers javadoc style documentation of BeanShell script files.
<p/>

<h3>Interpreter Modes</h3>

The following commands affect general modes of operation of the interpreter.

<table border="1" cellpadding="5">
<tr><td>exit()</td><td>
Exit the interpreter.  (Also Control-D).
</td></tr>
<tr><td>show()</td><td>
Turn on "show" mode which prints the result of every
evaluation that is not of void type.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>setAccessibility()</td><td>
Turn on access to private and protected members of Java classes.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>server()</td><td>
Launch the remote access mode, allowing remote access
to the interpreter from a web browser or telnet client.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>debug()</td><td>
Turns on debug mode.  Note: this is very verbose, 
unstructured output and is primarily of interest to developers.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>setStrictJava()</td><td>
Turn on "strict Java" mode which enforces Java
compatibility by dissallowing loose types and undeclared variables.
</td></tr>
</table>

<p/><h3>Output</h3>

The following commands are used for output:

<table border="1" cellpadding="5">
<tr><td>print(), error()</td><td>
Print output to standard out or standard error.  print() always goes to the
console, whereas System.out may or may not be captured by a GUI console
or servlet.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>frame()</td><td>
Display the AWT or Swing component in a Frame
</td></tr>
</table>

<p/><h3>Source and Evaluation</h3>

The following commands are used for evaluation or to run external scripts or
applications:

<table border="1" cellpadding="5">
<tr><td>eval()</td><td>
Evaluate a string as if it were typed in the current scope.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>source()</td><td>
Source an external file into the current interpreter
</td></tr>
<tr><td>run(), bg()</td><td>
Run an external file in a subordinate interpreter or in a background
thread in a subordinate interpreter.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>exec()</td><td>
Run a native executable in the host OS
</td></tr>
</table>

<p/><h3>Utilities</h3>

The following commands are useful utilities:

<table border="1" cellpadding="5">
<tr><td>javap()</td><td>
Print the methods and fields of an object, similar to the output of javap
</td></tr>
<tr><td>which()</td><td>
Like the Unix 'which' command for executables.  Map the classpath and 
determine the location of the specified class.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>load(), save()</td><td> load a serializable object from a file
or save one to a file.  Special handling is provided for certain objects.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>object()</td><td>
Create an "empty" object context to hold variables; analogous to a Map.
</td></tr>
</table>

<p/><h3>Variables and Scope</h3>

The following commands affect the current scope:

<table border="1" cellpadding="5">
<tr><td>clear()</td><td>Clear all variables, methods and imports from
the current scope.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>unset()</td><td>Remove a variable from the current scope.
(Return it to the "undefined" state).
</td></tr>
<tr><td>setNameSpace()</td><td>
Set the current namespace to a specified scope.  Effectively bind the 
current scope to a new parent scope.
</td></tr>
</table>

<p/><h3>Classpath</h3>

The following commands manipulate or access the classpath:

<table border="1" cellpadding="5">
<tr><td>addClassPath(), setClassPath(), getClassPath()</td><td>
Modify the BeanShell classpath.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>reloadClasses()</td><td>
Reload a class or group of classes.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>getClass()</td><td>
Load a class explicitly taking into account the BeanShell classpath.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>getResource()</td><td>
Get a resource from the classpath.
</td></tr>
</table>

<p/><h3>Files and Directories</h3>

The following commands work with files, directories, and the working
directory:

<table border="1" cellpadding="5">
<tr><td>cd(), pwd(), dir(), rm(), mv(), cat()</td><td>
Unix Style file commands.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>pathToFile()</td><td>
Translate a relative path to an absolute path taking into account
the BeanShell current working directory.
</td></tr>
</table>

<p/><h3>Desktop and Class Browser</h3>

The following commands work with GUI tools:

<table border="1" cellpadding="5">
<tr><td>classBrowser(), browseClass()</td><td>
Open a class browser window or browse a specific class or object.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>desktop()</td><td>
Launch the BeanShell GUI desktop.
</td></tr>
<tr><td>setNameCompletion()</td><td>
Turn on or off name completion in the GUI console.
</td></tr>
</table>
<p/>

<note>
The dir() command is written in Java; primarily as a demonstration of how
to do this when desired.
</note>

<h2>Adding Commands to BeanShell</h2>
<p/>

Adding to the set of "prefab" commands supplied with BeanShell is as easy as 
writing any other BeanShell methods.  You simply have to place your 
script into a file named with the same name as the command and place the
file in the classpath under a bsh/commands/ path.  The command files can
be anywhere in the classpath - in your own directories or in a JAR file.
<p/>

For example, let's make a helloworld() command:

<example>
// File: helloworld.bsh
helloworld() { 
    print("Hello World!");
}
</example>

If we place helloworld.bsh in the classpath under the path bsh/commands/
we can now use helloworld() just like any other BeanShell command.
<p/>

BeanShell command scripts can contain any number of overloaded forms of the
method, e.g.:

<example>
// File: helloworld.bsh
helloworld() { print("Hello World!"); }
helloworld( String msg ) { print(msg); }
</example>

You can also implement BeanShell commands directly in Java as compiled class 
files which are dynamically loaded when needed.   The dir() command is an 
example of a BeanShell command that is implemented in Java.   See it for
an example.
<p/>

<h2>Commands Scope</h2>

BeanShell commands are always sourced into the 'global' scope.
A useful feature of BeanShell for command writers is the 'this.caller'
reference, which allows you to create side effects in the caller's scope.
For example:

<example>
// File: setvar.bsh
fooSetter() {
    this.caller.foo=42;
}
</example>

The above command has the effect that after running it the variable 'foo'
will be set in the current scope. e.g.:

<example>
fooSetter();
print( foo ); // 42
</example>

It would not have been correct in this example for the command to refer 
to 'super', as that would simply always point to the global scope.

<h2>Getting the Caller Context</h2>

We mentioned earlier in this manual the difference between the 'super' or 
parent context of a method and the caller's context.  
The 'super' of a method is always
the context in which the method was defined.  But the caller may be any context
in which the method is used.  In the following example,
the parent context of foo() and the caller context of foo() are the same:

<example>
foo() { ... }
foo();
</example>

But this is not always the case, as for bar() in the following example:

<example>
foo() { 
    bar() { ... }
    ...
}

// somewhere
fooObject.bar();
</example>

The special "magic" field reference: 'this.caller' makes it possible 
to reach the context of whomever called bar().  The 'this.caller' reference 
always refers to the calling context of the current method context.
<p/>

<img src="caller.gif"/>
<p/>

The diagram above shows the foo() and bar() scopes, along with the caller's
scope access via 'this.caller'.
<p/>

The most common example of where this is useful is in writing
BeanShell commands.  
BeanShell command methods are always loaded into the global 
scope.  If you refer to 'super' from your command you will simply 
get 'global'.  Often it is desirable to write commands that explicitly have 
side effects in the caller's scope.  The ability to do so makes it possible to
write new kinds of commands that have the appearance of being "built-in" 
to the language.  
<p/>

A good example of this is the eval() BeanShell command.  eval() evaluates
a string as if it were typed in the current context.  To do this, it sends
the string to an instance of the BeanShell interpreter.  But when it does
so it tells the interpreter to evaluate the string in a specific namespace:
the namespace of the caller; using this.caller.

<example>
    eval("a=5");
    print( a ); // 5
</example>

You can follow the call chain further back if you want to by chaining
the '.caller' reference, like so:

<example>
    this.caller.caller...;
</example>

Or, more generally, another magic reference 'this.callstack' returns an
array of bsh.NameSpace objects representing the full call "stack".  This is
an advanced topic for developers that we'll discuss in another location.

<h2>Getting the Invocation Text</h2>

You can get specific information about the invocation of a method
using namespace.getInvocationLine() and namespace.getInvocationText().
The most important use for this is in support of the ability to write an
assert() method for unit tests that automatically prints the assertion text.

<example>
assert( boolean condition ) 
{
    if ( condition )
        print( "Test Passed..." );
    else {
        print(
            "Test FAILED: "
            +"Line: "+ this.namespace.getInvocationLine()
            +" : "+this.namespace.getInvocationText()
            +" : while evaluating file: "+getSourceFileInfo()
        );
        super.test_failed = true;
    }
}
</example>

<h2>Working With Class Identifiers</h2>

You may have noticed that certain BeanShell commands such as javap(),
which(), and browseClass() which take a class as an argument can accept any 
type of argument, including a plain Java class identifier.  For example,
all of the following are legal:

<example>
javap( class ); // use a class type directly
javap( someobject ); // uses class of object
javap( "java.lang.Thread" ); // Uses string name of class
javap( java.lang.Thread );  // Use plain class identifier
</example>

In the last case above we used the plain Java class identifier 
java.lang.Thread.  In Beanshell this resolves to a bsh.Name.ClassIdentifier
reference.  You can get the class for a ClassIdentifier using the 
Name.identifierToClass() method.  Here is an example of how to work
with all of the above, converting the argument to a class type:

<example>
    if ( o instanceof Name.ClassIdentifier )
        clas = this.namespace.identifierToClass(o);
    if ( o instanceof String)
        clas = this.namespace.getClass((String)o);
    else if ( o instanceof Class )
        clas = o;
    else
        clas = o.getClass();
</example>


</section>

