<section>
<name>Introduction</name>

This document is about BeanShell. 
BeanShell is a small, free, embeddable, Java source interpreter with 
object scripting language features, written in Java.  BeanShell executes 
standard Java statements and expressions but also extends Java into the 
scripting domain with common scripting language conventions and syntax.
<p/>

<h2>History</h2>

A long time ago, back in the summer of 1993 while working at Southwestern
Bell Technology Resources, I was infatuated with the Tcl/Tk scripting 
language.  At the time I was also playing around a bit with a 
language called Oak written by James Gosling at Sun. 
Little did I know that within just a few years Oak would not only spark the 
Java revolution, but that I would be writing one of the first books on 
the Java language for O'Reilly &amp; Associates and creating Java's first 
scripting language, BeanShell, using ideas from Tcl.
<p/>

BeanShell's first public release was not until 1997, but I had been
poking at it in one form or another for some time before that. BeanShell 
became truly practical when Sun added reflection to the Java language in 
version 1.1.  After that and after having seen its value in helping me create 
examples and snippets for the second edition of my book, I decided to try to 
polish it up and release it.
<p/>

BeanShell has slowly, but steadily gained popularity since then.  It has
grown in fits and spurts as its contributor's time has allowed.  But recently
BeanShell has achieved a sort of critical mass.  BeanShell is distributed with
Emacs as part of the JDE and with Sun Microsystem's NetBeans / Forte for Java
IDEs.  BeanShell is also bundled by BEA with their Weblogic application 
server.  We've had reports of BeanShell being used everywhere from 
the high energy physics laboratory CERN, to classrooms teaching programming
to nine year olds.  BeanShell is being used in everything from large 
financial applications all the way down to embedded systems floating in Buoys 
in the pacific ocean.   I attribute this success to the power of the open 
source development model and owe many thanks to everyone who has contributed.
<p/>

</section>
