<section>
<name>Quick Start</name>

Welcome to BeanShell.
This is a crash course to get you going.  We'll leave out some 
important options and details.  Please see the rest of the user's guide 
(which is not very long in its entirety) for more details.
<p/>

<h2>
Download and Run BeanShell
</h2>

Download the latest JAR file from http://www.beanshell.org
and start up BeanShell either in the graphical desktop mode or on 
the command line.
<p/>

If you just want to start playing around you may be able to to launch the 
BeanShell desktop by simply double clicking on the BeanShell JAR file.  More 
generally however you'll want to add the jar to your classpath so that you 
can work with your own classes and applications easily.
<p/>

To do this you can either drop the BeanShell JAR file into your Java 
<b>JRE/lib/ext/</b> folder <em>(Java 1.2 or later)</em> or add it to your 
classpath.

<example>
Place bsh.jar in your $JAVA_HOME/jre/lib/ext folder or add it to your
classpath like this:

<em>unix:</em>     export CLASSPATH=$CLASSPATH:bsh-xx.jar
<em>windows:</em>  set classpath %classpath%;bsh-xx.jar

    java bsh.Console       // run the graphical desktop
or
    java bsh.Interpreter   // run as text-only on the command line
or
    java bsh.Interpreter filename [ args ] // run script file
</example>
<p/>


<tip>From within BeanShell scripts or the command line you can to BeanShell's
classpath using the addClassPath() command.</tip>
<p/>

The above examples show how to run BeanShell interactively for experimentation
and how to run BeanShell scripts from the command line.
It's also possible to use BeanShell inside your own Java applications,
to run BeanShell in a remote server mode, as a servlet, or even in an applet.
<p/>

<h2>
The BeanShell Desktop and Console Windows
</h2>

Upon starting the BeanShell in GUI mode one console window will open.  
By right clicking on the desktop background you can open additional 
console windows and other tools such as a simple class browser.
<p/>

Each console window effectively runs a separate bsh interpreter.
Within the graphical console you have basic command history, line editing,
cut and paste, and even class and variable name completion.  From any console 
you can open a simple editor window for that console.  In it you can write 
scripts and hit the 'eval' button to evaluate them in the attached console's
workspace. 
<p/>

<h2>
Java Statements and Expressions
</h2>

At the prompt you can type standard Java statements, expressions, and
method declarations.
Statements and expressions are all of the normal things that you'd say
inside a Java method: e.g. variable declarations and assignments, 
method calls, loops, conditionals, etc.  
<p/>

You can use these exactly as they would appear in Java,
however in BeanShell you also have the option of working with "loosely typed"
variables.  That is, you can simply be lazy and not declare the types of
variables that you use (both primitives and objects).  BeanShell will only
signal an error if you attempt to misuse the actual type of the variable.
<p/>

Here are some examples:
<example>
foo = "Foo";    
four = (2 + 2)*2/2;
print( foo + " = " + four );  // print() is a BeanShell command

// Do a loop
for (i=0; i&lt;5; i++)
    print(i);   

// Pop up a frame with a button in it
button = new JButton( "My Button" );
frame = new JFrame( "My Frame" );
frame.getContentPane().add( button, "Center" );
frame.pack();
frame.setVisible(true);
</example>
<p/>

<h2>
Useful BeanShell Commands
</h2>

In the previous example we used a convenient "built-in" BeanShell command 
called print(), to display values.  print() does pretty
much the same thing as System.out.println() except that it insures that the
output always goes to the command line.  print() also displays some types
of objects (such as arrays) more verbosely than Java would.  

Another related command is show(), which toggles on and off automatic 
display of the result of every line you type.
<p/>

Here are a few other examples of BeanShell commands:

<ul>
<li> source(), run()  - Read a bsh script into this interpreter, or run it
in a new interpreter</li>
<li> frame()  - Display a GUI component in a Frame or JFrame.</li>
<li> load(),  save() - Load or save serializable objects to a file.</li>
<li> cd(), cat(), dir(), pwd(), etc.  - Unix-like shell commands</li>
<li> exec() - Run a native application </li>
</ul>

<p/>
See the complete list of BeanShell commands for more information.
<p/>

<tip>
BeanShell commands are not really "built-in" but are simply BeanShell scripted
methods that are automatically loaded from the classpath.  You can add your 
own scripts to the classpath to extend the basic command set.
</tip>

<h2>
Scripted Methods
</h2>

You can declare and use methods in bsh just as you would in a Java class.

<example>
int addTwoNumbers( int a, int b ) {
    return a + b;
}

sum = addTwoNumbers( 5, 7 );  // 12
</example>


Bsh methods may also have dynamic (loose) argument and return types.  

<example>
add( a, b ) {
    return a + b;
}

foo = add(1, 2);            // 3
foo = add("Oh", " baby");   // "Oh baby"
</example>

<h2>
Scripted Objects
</h2>

In BeanShell, as in JavaScript and Perl, method "closures" allow you to create
scripted objects.  You can turn the results of a method call into an object
reference by having the method return the special value <strong>this</strong>.
You can then use the reference to refer to any variables set during the method 
call.  Useful objects need methods of course, so in BeanShell scripted methods 
may also contain methods at any level.  For example:

<example>
foo() {
    print("foo");
    x=5;

    bar() {
        print("bar");
    }

    return this;
}

myfoo = foo();    // prints "foo"
print( myfoo.x ); // prints "5"
myfoo.bar();      // prints "bar"
</example>

If this seems strange to don't worry. Please see the user's manual for a 
more thorough explanation.
<p/>

<h2>Implementing Interfaces</h2>
<p/>
<em>Note: implementing arbitrary interfaces requires BeanShell be running 
under a Java 1.3 environment or higher</em>
<p/>

You can use the standard Java anonymous inner class syntax to implement an
interface type with a script.  For example:

<example>
ActionListener scriptedListener = new ActionListener() {
    actionPerformed( event ) { ... }
}
</example>

But more generally, you can simply use any BeanShell scripted object - i.e. 
any <em>'this'</em> type reference like myFoo in the previous example - as
any Java interface type, within your scripts.  When Java code calls methods 
on the interface the corresponding scripted methods will be invoked to handle 
them.  For passing references to BeanShell methods outside of your script,
you can also perform an explicit cast where necessary.  Please see the user
manual for details.
<p/>

You don't have to script all of the methods of an interface.  You can opt to
script only those that you intend to call if you want to.  
The calling code will simply throw an exception if it tries to 
invoke a method that isn't defined.
If you wish to override the behavior of a large number of methods - say to
produce a "dummy" adapter for logging - you can implement a special method
signature: invoke(name, args) in your scripted object. The invoke() method
is called to handle any undefined method invocations:

<example>
ml = new MouseListener() {
    mousePressed( event ) { ... }
    // handle the rest
    invoke( name, args ) { print("Method: "+name+" invoked!");
}
</example>

<h2>Calling BeanShell From Your Application</h2>

You can evaluate text and run scripts from within your application by
creating an instance of the BeanShell interpreter and using the eval()
or source() commands.  You may pass in variable references to objects you 
wish to use in scripts via the set() method and retrieve results with the 
get() method.

<example>
import bsh.Interpreter;
...

Interpreter i = new Interpreter();
i.set("foo", 5);
i.eval("bar = foo*10");
System.out.println("bar = "+i.get("bar") );
</example>

<tip>In the above example the eval() method also returned the value of bar as
the result of the evaluation.</tip>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

We hope this brief introduction gets you started.  Please see the full user
manual for more details.  We will strive the keep the documentation up to date
but we will always lag behind.  So check the mailing lists and change log for 
the application if you really want to know what's going on.


</section>


