<section>
<name>BshServlet and In-Container Scripting</name>

<pre>
I know many of you are using BeanShell in your unit testing.  I am interested
in the kinds of tools you have developed and what you'd like to see in a 
standard BeanShell unit test framework. 

A while back I posted a small test servlet that could be used to execute 
bsh scripts inside a servlet container.  I have since moved this servlet 
into a package in the main distribution in a way that I think can serve as 
the basis for simple in-container unit testing.

The new bsh.servlet package includes a standard BshServlet that accepts a
script via the POST method.  The servlet captures output, optionally including
stdout and stderr, from the script and returns it along with any return value.

Scripts have access to the servlet environment through the variables 

  bsh.httpServletRequest
  bsh.httpServletResponse

and can generate the a full response if they wish by specifying raw output
from a servlet parameter.

You can use the servlet interactively through a form that it generates, or,
more importantly, through the new command line launcher bsh.Remote (analagous
to bsh.Interpreter).  bsh.Remote accepts a URL for a target bsh interpreter 
and one or more file names to send to that server, printing the results.  

  java bsh.Remote http://localhost/bshservlet/eval test1.bsh

BshServlet can handle scripts posted from the launcher, but bsh.Remote also 
supports the traditional (telnet style) remote bsh server mode via the new 
"bsh://" url. 

  java bsh.Remote bsh://localhost:1234/ test1.bsh

In either case, if bsh.Remote can parse the retun value as an integer it will 
return it as the exit status to the command line.  You can also do this from 
a script using the method bsh.Remote.eval().

You can grab one of the sample application WAR files here:

<a href="http://www.beanshell.org/bshservlet.war">bshservlet.war</a>
<a href="http://www.beanshell.org/bshservlet-wbsh.war">bshservlet-wbsh.war</a> <em>Rename this file to "bshservlet.war" for use.</em>

The first WAR assumes that BeanShell has been installed in your application
server's classpath.  It includes only the web.xml file necessary to deploy
an instance of the test servlet and an index.html README file.  To install 
BeanShell in the Tomcat server classpath place the bsh.jar file in common/lib.  
To use BeanShell in Weblogic you must upgrade its version of the package.  
See <a href="weblogic.html">Upgrading BeanShell in Weblogic</a>.

The second WAR (-wbsh) includes bsh-1.2b5 inside the WAR.  This includes 
everything you need to just drop the WAR into an application server.  (Note
that bshservlet-wbsh.war will still *not* work in Weblogic 6.x unless you 
upgrade Weblogic's version.  
See <a href="weblogic.html">Upgrading BeanShell in Weblogic</a>.

To use the servlet for testing your own applications simply deploy an 
instance of the test servlet in your WAR file.  This will allow it to share 
a classloader with your webapp so that you can test things like application 
classes and EJB local homes.  Since the servlet is included in the standard 
distribution, all that is necessary to do this is to add an entry to your 
web.xml file.  
See the <a href="example-web.xml">example web.xml file</a> or the sample WARs above.

I think that the ability to dynamically execute unit tests in the container
without building, deploying, and re-deploying makes this a very powerful
tool.  Please let me know what you think.
</pre>

</section>
